Linjian Ma

+1 217 979 7114 \diamond lma16@illinois.edu \diamond linjianma.github.io github/Linkedin: linjianma

RESEARCH STATEMENT

My research interests lie in the intersection of numerical linear algebra, high performance computing and quantum computing. In particular, I'm now focusing on developing efficient numerical algorithms and parallel systems for tensor computations with applications in data analytics and quantum simulations. Previously, I worked on optimization and efficient compression methods of neural networks.

EDUCATION BACKGROUNDS

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign PhD, Computer Science, Advisor: Edgar Solomonik Area: Scientific Computing	August 2019 - Expected 2023 GPA: 3.95/4.0
University of California, Berkeley	August 2018 - May 2019
MEng, Computer Science, Advisor: <i>Michael Mahoney</i> Track: Data Science & Systems	Major GPA: 3.94/4.0
University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign	August 2016 - May 2018
MS, Mechanical Engineering, Advisor: N.R. Aluru	GPA: 3.97/4.0
Concentration: Computational Science and Engineering	
Zhejiang University	August 2012 - June 2016
BE, Energy Engineering, Advisor: Tao Wang and Zhongyang Luo	GPA: $3.95/4.0$
Graduate with Honors, Chu Kochen Honors College	

HONORS AND AWARDS

Kuck Computational Science & Engineering Scholarship, UIUC	2020
Computer Science Gene Golub Fellowship, UIUC	2019
Graduate with Honor, ZJU	2016
Meritorious Winner, Mathematical Contest In Modeling (MCM)	2015
National Scholarship for Undergraduate, ZJU	2014
The First Class Scholarship for Outstanding Students, ZJU	2013 - 2014
The First Prize in China Undergraduates Mathematical Contest	2013

PRESENTATIONS

Upcoming presentations	SIAM'LA 2021, IPDPS 2021
First author presentations	SIAM'CSE 2021, PACT 2020, SIAM'PP 2020,
	Berkeley'SCseminar 2019, USNCCM 2017
Posters	SIAM'PP 2020 AAAI 2020

Posters SIAM'PP 2020, AAAI 2020

PUBLICATIONS

^[1] Navjot Singh, Linjian Ma, Hongru Yang, Edgar Solomonik, Comparison of Accuracy and Scalability of Gauss-Newton and Alternating Least Squares for CP Decomposition, SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing (SISC), 2021. [link]

- [2] Linjian Ma and Edgar Solomonik, Efficient Parallel CP Decomposition with Pairwise Perturbation and Multisweep Dimension Tree, International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium (IPDPS'21), 2021. [link]
- [3] **Linjian Ma***, Jiayu Ye*, and Edgar Solomonik, AutoHOOT: Automatic High-Order Optimization for Tensors, International Conference on Parallel Architectures and Compilation Techniques (PACT'20), 2020. [link]
- [4] Sheng Shen, Zhen Dong, Jiayu Ye, **Linjian Ma**, Zhewei Yao, Amir Gholami, Michael W. Mahoney, Kurt Keutzer, Q-BERT: Hessian Based Ultra Low Precision Quantization of BERT, AAAI'20, 2020. [link]
- [5] **Linjian Ma***, Gabe Montague*, Jiayu Ye*, Zhewei Yao, Amir Gholami, Kurt Keutzer, Michael W. Mahoney, Inefficiency of K-FAC for Large Batch Size Training, AAAI'20, 2020. [link]
- [6] **Linjian Ma**, Pikee Priya, and N. R. Aluru, A Multiscale Model for Electrochemical Reactions in LSCF Based Solid Oxide Cells, *Journal of the Electrochemical Society*, 2018. [link]

PREPRINTS AND TECHNICAL REPORTS

- [1] **Linjian Ma** and Edgar Solomonik, Fast and Accurate Randomized Algorithms for Low-rank Tensor Decompositions, *arXiv:2104.01101*, 2021. [link]
- [2] **Linjian Ma** and Edgar Solomonik, Accelerating Alternating Least Squares for Tensor Decomposition by Pairwise Perturbation, *arXiv:1811.10573*, 2018. [link]
- [3] **Linjian Ma**, A Multiscale Model for the Oxide Ion Conducting and Proton Conducting Solid Oxide Cells, *MS thesis, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign*, 2018. [link]

RESEARCH EXPERIENCES

Lab for Parallel Numerical Algorithms, UIUC

August 2019 - Now

Research Assistant, Advisor: Edgar Solomonik

Topic: On efficient algorithms and systems for numerical tensor algebra

Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory

May 2020 - August 2020

Research Intern, Advisor: Chao Yang

Topic: Low-rank approximation in simulations of quantum algorithms

Wave Computing & Berkeley AI Research (BAIR)

May 2019 - August 2019

Machine Learning Intern

Topic: Compressing large scale neural networks based on second-order information

RiseLab, UC Berkeley

August 2018 - May 2019

Research Assistant, Advisor: Michael Mahoney

Capstone project: Second-order optimization of neural network learning

Beckman Institute, UIUC

August 2016 - December 2017

Research Assistant, Advisor: N.R. Aluru

Thesis: A multiscale model for the oxide ion conducting and proton conducting solid oxide cells

SERVICES

Teaching Assistant CS 450 Numerical Analysis (Fall 2020)

SKILLS

Programming Languages C/C++, Python, Go, Bash, Matlab, CUDA

ML Frameworks Pytorch, TensorFlow